Guide to the Edith Wharton Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
In her letters to Lapsley, Wharton frequently comments on Henry James. Among the more revealing letters are those of September 21, 1908; July 6, 1911; September 4, 1911; September 20, 1912; November 11, 1912; February 21, 1914; November 8, 1914; and October 14, 1915. Letters between February 13 and May 27, 1913 relate to Wharton's efforts to help raise $5,000 for James's seventieth birthday, a gift which ironically provoked James's ire and caused Wharton much distress. Included with the letter of March 23 is a copy of the subscription letter sent to potential contributors among his friends and a list of the eventual subscribers. A letter of November 4, 1915 to Wharton from Theodora Bosanquet, James's secretary, comments on his health and activities. A letter of December 17, 1915 reveals Wharton's reaction to James's impending death ("All my 'blue distances' will be shut out forever when he goes"), and a letter of March 6, 1916 discusses James's passing. A revealing letter is a copy of Wharton's letter to James's niece Margaret in June, 1916, about the publication of James's letters.
As an indication of Wharton's frank comments on friends and other writers, she says of André Gide in a letter of October 18, 1918: "He is a mass of quivering 'susceptibilities,' & invents grievances when he can't find them ready made. Luckily he is so charming that one ends by not noticing."
Series VIII, the Oscar Lichtenberg bequests (Box 61), contains letters from about twelve correspondents, along with the page proofs of Wharton's short story "Autres Temps."
Included in the correspondence are twenty-one letters from Wharton to Richard Watson Gilder, the editor of the Century magazine. In this correspondence Wharton discusses, among other things, her exploration of Italian villas and gardens and her subsequent articles on them for Century (1902-1903), as well as later submissions to the magazine. In a letter of July 25, 1908 she defends her story "Life" against charges of lack of realism.
Letters to Robert Underwood Johnson, another Century editor, from 1900 to 1911 also discuss short story submissions to the magazine and show Wharton's stern defense of her form and punctuation. (See especially a lengthy letter of May 17, 1911.)
Series IX, Percy Lubbock material (Box 62), contains holograph and typed reminiscences about Edith Wharton from a number of her friends which Lubbock gathered for his Portrait of Edith Wharton (1946). Included are very informative and often touching reminiscences (varying from one to almost fifty pages) by Bernard Berenson, Emil Blanche, Margaret Chanler, Sir Kenneth Clark, Robert Norton, Sara Norton, John Hugh Smith, Gaillard Lapsley, and others who were close to Wharton.
Series X, the Georges Markow-Totevy bequest (Box 63), consists of material on Edith Wharton gathered by Markow-Totevy for an intended study of her life and work. The collection contains letters (originals and copies) to Wharton from Bernard Berenson, Henry James, Paul Bourget, and Vernon Lee, among others; and also letters from a number of Wharton's friends (Margaret Chanler, Jean Cocteau, and Elisina Tyler, etc.) to Markow-Totevy. Also included are extracts from Wharton's journals in the 1930s, notes from interviews with several of her acquaintances (Sir Eric Maclagan, Vicomte Charles de Noailles, John Hugh Smith, Jules de la Forêt-Divonne, and Jeanne Fridèrich, her secretary for several years), copies of several of her stories and poems, and several photographs (mostly negatives) of her homes.
Series XI, the Louis Auchincloss gift (Boxes 64-65), consists of six large spiral binders (entitled "The Letters of Edith Wharton") containing letters from and about Wharton and material related to her life and writings, chronologically arranged. The letters span the years 1881 to 1938 and discuss many aspects of Wharton's life and work. Wharton's own letters, most of which are to Mildred Bliss or Walter and Eunice Maynard, date between 1891 and 1937. Two early letters (1891) give condolences to Mrs. William Wetmore on the death of her sister and Wharton's friend Louise Wetmore (Box 64, folder 1790). Although the Wharton letters generally say little about her writing, a letter of May 24, 1900 to Eunice Maynard discusses her first book, The Decoration of Houses (1897). A letter of May 24, 1906 discusses Wharton's automobile travels in England and France and mentions the success of The House of Mirth (Box 64, folder 1791). Another letter to Eunice Maynard on June 12, 1913 discusses her divorce of that year; and a letter to Mildred Bliss on April 5, 1913 concerns the disastrous intended monetary gift to Henry James on his seventieth birthday. Several letters from 1915 to 1918 (Box 64, folder 1792) discuss the war, her charity work, and The Book of the Homeless, while several lengthy letters to her cousin Thomas Rhinelander in October, 1918 show her distress over the tragic death of his son in an air fight over France.
Volume III of "The Letters of Edith Wharton" (Box 64, folder 1792) contains a two-page description from an unidentified source of Wharton's last home, the chateau Ste. Claire, at Hyères, France. Scattered throughout the six volumes are photos of Wharton, her friends, and her homes Ste. Claire and Pavillon Colombe. Also in Volume III is a list of the provisions of Wharton's various trusts from her parents' wills (1882, 1901). Letters of May 4, June 28, and December 16, 1923, and May 29, 1924 relate to her honorary Yale degree. A lengthy letter to Mary Cadwalader Jones on February 21, 1921 concerns the dramatization of The Age of Innocence, while a letter to Margaret "Daisy" Chanler on June 9, 1925 reveals her interpretation of the "key" to her novel A Mother's Recompense and discusses the early critical reception of this work. Several letters in late 1927 to Mildred Bliss discuss Wharton's relationship with Walter Berry and the effect of his death on her. A copy of a letter to Bliss on February 10, 1928 states her intention to sell her properties and use the proceeds to endow a sanitarium in France.
Volume V (Box 65, folder 1794) contains a 1928 Christmas card with a short poem to the Lawrence Grant Whites. An interesting letter to White of March 29, 1932 speaks of Wharton's quarrel with "resurrected words." "Since good usage has ceased to be recognized as the determining factor in American speech, or writing, words are revived, or composed afresh, in a spirit of tiresome pedantry... ." The same letter applauds Aldous Huxley's Brave New World as "the biggest English satire since Gulliver" and speaks favorably of Huxley as a neighbor. Another letter to White on April 13, 1936 comments on the stage version of Ethan Frome.
In Volume VI (Box 65, folder 1795), letters to Gaillard Lapsley from Elisina Tyler, Beatrix Farrand, and Robert Norton (all August, 1937) recall Edith Wharton's final days before her death; and other letters from Norton, Bernard Berenson, and Charles Seymour to Lapsley are concerned with Wharton's will. A rather lengthy letter from Charles Du Bos to Percy Lubbock on August 6, 1938 comments on the distance at which Wharton held herself from even her closest friends. A letter from Lubbock to Lapsley on December 22, 1938 outlines his plans for his proposed Portrait of Edith Wharton.
The final item in Volume VI is a genealogical chart of the Jones family ("Chart of John Jones III").
Series XII, Other Papers (Box 66), contains copies of a number of articles about Edith Wharton and her world, reviews of several book-length studies, a copy of Henry James's will, obituary notices of Walter Berry and Walter Gay, an untitled holograph poem by Minnie Bourget, and items relating to the printing of an Edith Wharton Commemorative Stamp in 1980.
Oversize material (Box 67) contains items from the Personal Papers and Photographs series.
American literature -- 20th Century; Charities -- France; Drama -- 20th Century; Fiction -- 20th Century; Poetry, Modern -- 20th Century; Short stories, American -- 20th Century; World War, 1914-1918 -- France; France -- Description and travel; Newport (R.I.) -- Social life and customs; Paris (France) -- Intellectual life; Photographs; Authors; Novelists; Women authors; Auchincloss, Louis, 1917-2010; Beerbohm, Max, Sir, 1872-1956; Benson, Arthur Christopher, 1862-1925; Berenson, Bernard, 1865-1959; Berry, Walter, 1859-1927; Bourget, Paul, 1852-1935; Brownell, W. C. (William Crary), 1851-1928; Chanler, Margaret; Clark, Kenneth, 1903-1983; Conrad, Joseph, 1857-1924; Edel, Leon, 1907-1997; Farrand, Beatrix, 1872-1959; Gardner, Isabella Stewart, 1840-1924; Gide, André, 1869-1951; Gilder, Richard Watson, 1844-1909; Gillet, Louis, 1876-1943; Gosse, Edmund, 1849-1928; James, Henry, 1843-1916; Johnson, Robert Underwood, 1853-1937; Jones, Mary Cadwalader; Lubbock, Percy, 1879-1965; Mitchell, S. Weir (Silas Weir), 1829-1914; Norton, Sara, 1864-; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Sargent, John Singer, 1856-1925; Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937; Cobden-Sanderson, Richard; Charles Scribner's Sons; Curtis Brown Ltd; D. Appleton and Company; Dodd, Mead & Company; Macmillan & Co; National Institute of Arts and Letters (U.S.); E. Plon, Nourrit and Co
- Writings, 1895-1976; Series I; 9; (22 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Writings, is divided into three main subseries: Books, Shorter Works, and Notebooks. Within Books and Shorter Works, items are arranged alphabetically by title. The subseries Notebooks is arranged chronologically.
  - BOOKS
    - The Age of Innocence
      - Outline, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2-14)
      - Correction sheet, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Reviews, 1920, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Dramatization by Margaret Ayers, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17-20)
      - Program for dramatization, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Artemis to Acteon
      - Page proofs (incomplete), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Reviews, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - The Associates
      - Synopsis, holograph manuscript and typescript (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Holograph manuscript and typescript (fragment) (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - A Backward Glance
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26-43)
      - Typescript (incomplete) with index (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - Correction sheet, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - Typescript (in French), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46-48)
      - Reviews, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - The Buccaneers
      - Outline, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 50)
      - Holograph notes, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 51)
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 52-67)
      - Holograph fragments, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 68)
      - Synopsis, typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 69)
      - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 70-78)
      - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Charity
      - Holograph manuscript (incomplete), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - The Children
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 81-97)
      - Typescript, correction sheet, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 98)
      - Reviews, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Crucial Instances
      - Reviews, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - The Custom of the Country
      - Holograph notes, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 101)
      - Holograph manuscript (incomplete), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 102-03)
      - Reviews, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 104-06)
    - Disintegration
      - Holograph manuscript (incomplete), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 107)
      - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 108-10)
    - Efficiency
      - Holograph manuscript (incomplete), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - Ethan Frome
      - Holograph manuscript (incomplete), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 112-13)
      - Notebook ("French Draft"), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 114)
      - Notebook ("French Draft"), photocopy, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 115)
      - Review, 1912 Feb 4 (Box 5, Folder 116)
      - Dramatization by Owen and Donald Davis: preface, holograph manuscript, 1935 Jan (Box 5, Folder 117)
        - Holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 118-20)
        - Drama reviews, 1936, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 121-22)
      - "The Writing of Ethan Frome"
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Box 32, folder 1010
    - Everest
      - Holograph manuscript (incomplete), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 123)
      - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - France
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - French Ways and Their Meanings
      - Holograph manuscript and typescript (incomplete) (Box 5, Folder 126)
      - Typescript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 127)
    - The Fruit of the Tree
      - Reviews, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - Ghosts: preface
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 129)
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 130)
      - Page proofs, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - A Gift From the Grave
      - Reviews, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - Glimpses of the Moon
      - Outline, holograph and typescript (Box 5, Folder 133)
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 134-48)
      - Correction sheet, typescript, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 149)
    - The Gods Arrive
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 150-77)
      - Correction sheet, typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 178)
      - Review, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 179)
    - The Greater Inclination
      - Reviews (in notebook), 1899 (Box 7, Folder 180)
    - The House of Mirth
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 181-205)
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 206-12)
      - Typescript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 213-15)
      - Reviews, 1905, 1908, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 216-17)
      - Program for dramatic adaptation by John Tillinger, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 218)
    - Hudson River Bracketed
      - Outline, holograph, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 219)
      - Summary, typescript, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 220)
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 221-34)
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 235-57)
      - Correction sheets, typescript, 1928, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 258)
    - Human Nature
      - Reviews, 1933, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 259)
    - Italian Backgrounds
      - Holograph manuscript ("What the Hermits Saw"), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 260)
    - The Keys of Heaven (L. de Lassy version)
      - Holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 261-62)
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 263)
    - The Keys of Heaven. (Olney-Beecher version)
      - Holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 264)
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 265)
    - Life and I (Autobiographical fragment)
      - Holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 266)
      - Photocopy, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 267)
    - Literature: A Novel
      - Notebook, 1913 (Box 10, Folder 268)
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 269)
      - Book I
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 270-72)
        - First draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 273-74)
        - First draft, typescript, corrected carbon, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 275-76)
        - Second draft, typescript, corrected (Box 10, Folder 277-78)
        - Third draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 279-80)
        - Revised draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 281-82)
        - Draft, typescript, incomplete, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 283)
    - Love Among the Ruins
      - Synopsis, holograph, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 284)
    - The Marne
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 10, Folder 285-86)
    - The Mother's Recompense
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 287-96)
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 297-304)
      - Reviews, 1925 (Box 11, Folder 305)
    - The New Day
      - Holograph manuscript and typescript, corrected (Box 11, Folder 306)
    - The Reef
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 11, Folder 307-20)
      - Revised holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 11, Folder 321-26)
      - Le Récif (French translation), holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 327)
      - Le Récif, typescript, corrected (first version, incomplete), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 328-32)
      - Le Récif, typescript, corrected (second version) (Box 12, Folder 333-38)
      - Reviews, 1912-13 (Box 12, Folder 339-40)
    - Son at the Front
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 341-50)
    - Summer
      - Holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 351-62)
      - Reviews, 1917 (Box 12, Folder 363)
    - The Touchstone
      - Reviews, 1900 (Box 12, Folder 364)
    - Twilight Sleep
      - Holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 365-84)
      - Reviews, 1927, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 385-87)
    - The Valley of Decision
      - Background material (Box 14, Folder 388)
      - Notebook, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 389)
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 390)
      - Holograph manuscript (incomplete), n.d. (Box 14, Folder 391-407)
      - Illustrations, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 408)
      - La Valle di Decisione, (Italian translation, incomplete), 1932 (Box 14, Folder 409-14)
      - Reviews, 1902 (Box 14, Folder 415)
    - Verses
      - Holograph manuscript (incomplete), n.d. (Box 14, Folder 416)
    - Xingu and Other Stories
      - Reviews, 1917 (Box 14, Folder 417)
  - SHORTER WORKS
    - Short Stories
      - "After Holbein": holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 418)
      - "Afterward": holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 419-21)
      - "Antiphonissa"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 422)
        - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 423)
      - "Atrophy": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 424)
      - "Beatrice Palmato"
        - Synopsis, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 425)
        - Holograph manuscript (fragment), n.d. (Box 15, Folder 426)
      - "Behind the Government": typescript, corrected (incomplete) (Box 15, Folder 427)
      - "The Best Policy": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 428-29)
      - "Bewitched": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 430-31)
      - "A Bottle of Perrier": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 432-34)
      - "The Children's Hour"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 435)
        - Typescript (first draft), corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 436)
        - Typescript, (second draft), corrected (Box 15, Folder 437)
      - "The Choice": page proof (incomplete), n.d. (Box 15, Folder 438)
      - "Cold Greenhouse": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 439)
      - "Confession": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 440-43)
      - "The Confessional": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 444-46)
      - "The Consolers": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 447)
      - "The Count": typescript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 15, Folder 448)
      - "Count Underlinden"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 449)
        - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 450)
      - "The Cruise of the Fleetwing"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 15, Folder 451)
        - Typescript (first draft), corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 452)
        - Typescript, (second draft), corrected (Box 15, Folder 453-54)
      - "A Dancing Partner": holograph manuscript (incomplete), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 455)
      - "The Daunt Diana" ("La Diana de la Collection Daunt"): French translation, typescript, corrected (Box 16, Folder 456)
      - "Dawn"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 457)
        - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 458)
      - "The Day of the Funeral"
        - Holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 459-60)
        - Typescript (incomplete), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 461)
      - "The Desert's Edge": holograph manuscript (incomplete), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 462)
      - "Diagnosis": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 463-64)
      - "Dieu d'Amour" ("A Castle in Cyprus") holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 465-66)
      - "Duration"
        - Synopsis, holograph and typescript (Box 16, Folder 467-68)
        - Holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 469)
        - Correction sheet, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 470)
      - "End of Day" holograph manuscript, corrected (Box 16, Folder 471)
      - "Exorcism"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 472)
        - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 473)
      - "The Eyes": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 474-75)
      - ["Facing the Facts"]: holograph manuscript (incomplete), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 476)
      - "False Dawn"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 477-80)
        - "Alba Infida" (Italian translation) typescript, corrected (Box 16, Folder 481-82)
      - "La Famille": typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 483)
      - "The Field of Honor": typescript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 484)
      - "Finishing Governess"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 485)
        - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 486)
      - "The First Born of Egypt": typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 487)
      - "A Glimpse": holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 488)
      - "A Granted Prayer"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 489)
        - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 490)
      - "The Great Miss Netherby"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 491)
        - Typescript (first draft), corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 492)
        - Typescript (second draft), corrected (Box 16, Folder 493)
      - "The Happy Isles"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 494-96)
        - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 497)
      - "Her Son": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 498-502)
      - "The Idealist": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 503)
      - "Images Marocaines"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 504)
        - Typescript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 505)
      - "In An Hour": holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 506)
      - "The Intruders"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 507)
        - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 508)
      - "Joy in the House": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 509-10)
      - "The Lamp of Psyche"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 511)
        - Printed copy, corrected, 1895 Oct (Box 17, Folder 512)
      - "Latmos": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 513)
      - "Logic": manuscript notebook, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 514)
      - "The Looking Glass" ("The Mirror"): holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 515-16)
      - "The Man Who Saved the World": typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 517)
      - "Miss Mary Pask": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 518)
      - "Miss Moynham"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 519)
        - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 520)
      - "Mr. Jones" ("The Parasite"): holograph manuscript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 521-23)
      - "Mother Earth": holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 524)